[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
hi this is priyanka raghavan for
software engineering radio
in this episode we will deep dive into
console the service
mesh from hashicorp and my guest today
is luke
kaiser console engineer at hashicorp
luke is also the maintainer and
co-creator of
atlantis an open source tool for
terraform collaboration
luke has given many talks in different
software engineering conferences so
really excited to have you on the show
welcome to the show luke
thank you so much for having me is there
anything else you would like listeners
to know about you
before we jump into console no i think
you
mostly covered it i engineer at
hashicorp i work on console
and prior to that i did a lot of devops
and
just regular development at a couple
other companies
perfect as you know we've done a couple
of episodes
on microservices as well as service
discovery
we did an episode two years back on
istio
the service mesh from google and four
years back
we talked about service discovery and
obviously a lot has changed over
sorry it's actually five years right
it's 20 21 so
we'll try to cover what's changed since
then yeah
so the first thing i need to ask before
we actually jump into console is could
you recap
for our listeners what is a service mesh
in your own words
so when we think about a surface mesh i
think
the the most common kind of way that
this this
looks is you have every single service
that you are running in your
architecture has a proxy
that runs in front of it and that proxy
captures the traffic that leaves your
service
and also captures the traffic that's
entering your service
now that you have this proxy in front of
every application
you're now able to control the traffic
that goes into and out of that
application
and that's kind of what a service mesh
is is
the ability now is like this mesh of
proxies
and now you can control where that
traffic goes uh whether or not it's
allowed into the application
and you can control all that through
through a control plane so i think
that's like
what when we think about surface mesh
that's kind of what the the basic
manifestation of it is
so in the 2016 episode which was episode
the guest james phil from console as
well he talked about
the architecture being a console agent
running on different nodes
and then the service discovery happens
through the
gossip protocol you know that's a gist
of what he said
what's new and or what's changed since
then
yeah so we have this division now
between the idea of service discovery
which is kind of the older concept
and this do this new world of service
mesh
and it's a little bit complicated like
what exactly is the difference between
these because
in the end you know it's just one
service calling another service
we'll just talk a little bit about
service discovery with service discovery
what we have is we have a list of all of
our applications
and all of their ip addresses and their
ports
we're able to know where this
application is and then from within
our application so for example say we
have a web service and it's trying to
call
the database the web service can can
look up
within the service discovery mechanism
okay where is this
database running and then it can direct
traffic over there
so this lookup can be done through
through dns was traditionally what it
would
how it would work so you would use like
examplecompany.database
and then the service discovery mechanism
would tell you oh the ip address for
that is
10.10.10.10 on and then i i can just
talk to that on port
whatever report so what's evolved since
then
is now the application instead of kind
of
participating in that service discovery
where it needs a way to find out
itself what the ip address is for the
database
instead the application talks through a
proxy
and so now that proxy is the thing
that's doing the lookup
for where the database is you look at
that and you say okay well that's what's
the point of the proxy then
my servers could have just done a dns
lookup but now that we have this proxy
there
the proxy can do so much more than just
do a dns lookup right
it can control where that traffic goes
it can
retry that traffic it can notice that
that application is down
and use like a circuit breaker pattern
where it doesn't send it traffic or
maybe it can fail over to
another data center where maybe the
database is actually up and running
that's really the evolution there is
that now we're kind of handing off this
where does my request go step
to the proxy and that gives us so much
more power
and the reason we didn't do that before
was a it was extra complexity that we
didn't need
but now that we have kind of this world
of microservices
and and dynamic services there is a lot
more
complexity in how our network works that
we do find ourselves
needing to program it add some smarts in
there
in addition with the rise of platforms
such as kubernetes
it's a lot easier to deploy that proxy
now
alongside all of our applications you
could imagine
back when when james phillips was on the
show in 2016 and we didn't have
kubernetes
if i were to tell you okay all you need
to do now
is deploy a proxy on every single vm
you're running
by every single application and
configure it with a
with a certificate and rotate that
certificate
that was a very large job
but now with some platforms like
kubernetes where
and again you'll see this pattern of
kind of programmability
where now we can kind of program what
the application actually runs
and what runs alongside it so concretely
i'm talking about how we now have this
concept of pods and we can actually add
containers docker images
to run alongside those pods now it's so
much easier
to add that proxy to all of our
applications
and that makes this pattern a lot more
viable
there is a lot of stuff that you've told
us in this
introduction but let's like sort of
break it down if i were to ask you
what are the main components of the
service mesh
so i think one you alluded to was of
course service discovery
right and and also i guess how how
healthy your resources are
right and then what are the other
components
yeah so the key pieces of information
that we needed to know are where are the
services so that's the service discovery
mechanism
so where is the database and what is
this ip address how can i route there
the second one is like you mentioned as
well like is the database
healthy can i route to that and that's
really all that we need
when we do start talking about which we
can talk about later
the idea of like multiple clusters then
we do need some some extra information
the other piece of information that we
need and it's very kind of important to
the service mesh
is is this service this web service
allowed to talk to this database so kind
of the
the authorization there is web allowed
to talk to db
so those are kind of the the information
we need and then
the components like the concrete
components involved
are the proxies themselves and then what
we call the control plane so
the application that's programming those
proxies and telling it
what each proxy should be doing so for
the last two months at work
i've been struggling with bringing up
open source api gateway so i just have
to ask you this before we
jump into console do i need to also have
an api gateway when i have a service
mesh
yeah that's a super super great question
yes the answer is
that the problems that an api gateway
solves
aren't being solved at the same time by
a service mesh
although i will say that the two
technology areas are becoming
increasingly overlapping
but when we talk about what we think
about with the service mesh
traditionally it's been service to
service traffic
so it's the web service that's talking
to the database it's the billing service
that's talking to
the payment service let's say and so
you're kind of talking about this
this services service traffic whereas an
api gateway
is obviously external consumers trying
to talk
in to to your api and so
the functionality is similar but a
little bit separate so
with api gateway you might have a bunch
of logic around
developer tokens who is this person
coming in are they allowed to access
this api
rate limiting etc etc so kind of more
you might have like admin panel that
lets you see which
developer tokens have been called in so
there is a little bit more functionality
kind of
as a result of having to manage the fact
that these are external clients
whereas for the service mesh typically
these are internal clients and so
we don't necessarily have a bunch of
tokens where we have to rate limit based
on that
instead we might do kind of like a
service level rate limiting the
functionality is overlapping
however they are kind of separate
concerns at this time
okay that makes sense let's jump into
console now you did touch upon service
discovery
how do services in console
discover other services the question i
wanted to ask was how do you
like bootstrap the entire systems do you
talk about dns but
maybe you can elaborate a bit more yeah
for sure
when we talk about for how it all gets
bootstrapped
you need the platform with the
information about where the services are
kind of needs to be there first so in
the case of
a platform like kubernetes or nomad or
ecs or one of these kind of container
schedulers
the platform already knows which
services are running
the process of bootstrapping for console
is kind of more about
starting console and then telling
console hey here's what's running in the
system
we already know what's running like a
bridge system basically that's going to
be
watching an api for instance the
kubernetes api watching for
for what's running there and then
telling console hey this is running
there
and we talk about something like a
platform like virtual machines where
there is no kind of
overriding scheduler that knows
everything
in that world the services actually need
to tell console like hey
i'm running in that world what we do is
we have
uh either via api or via config file
where when the service is running it
kind of tells console hey
hey i'm running here this is my ap
address this is my port
so that's kind of how we see the the
service discovery information get into
console
okay can you also touch upon like how do
you find out
if a resource is down on the health
monitoring how does that happen
again it's kind of this uh the split
between depending on which platform
you're running on
so in platforms like again kubernetes
nomad ecs those platforms actually
already have
the information about the health of each
service
and the reason they already have that
information is because
they need to make decisions about oh
this application is down i might need to
reschedule it or restart it or at least
give a warning to the user so these
systems already have this information
so in this case it's a matter of syncing
that information into console
and telling console hey kubernetes says
my web service is down
you should know that too so you don't
also wrote traffic there
now in addition to that which is kind of
configured on the platform side and
usually this is
active health checking so the platform
person who's running the service will
actually configure
uh alex for instance hey call me on my
slash health endpoint
every minute and if i don't respond with
the 200
treat me as unhealthy the platform will
then
park the services unhealthy we'll sync
that information into console we'll know
not to route to that service
or at least perform whatever we you know
whatever we want to do there
there is an additional type of health
checking called passive health checking
where we actually notice on our calls
between the different proxies
that hey i noticed that the platform
says the web service is healthy
but every single call that i'm making to
this instance is returning a 503
and so we're actually gonna be like okay
well i think the platform's wrong here i
actually think that that application is
unhealthy
and we're internally gonna mark that as
unhealthy and we're not gonna route to
it anymore
so there is a kind of almost two layers
there of health checking
so that's like kind of the platform view
of the world where they already own that
information and we just sync it to
console
and then when we look at a platform that
for instance virtual machines where
there is no overarching scheduler
in this platform console will be the one
that's doing the health checking so
you did allude to this earlier where our
architecture for virtual machines is we
have a console client
which is just a process running on every
virtual machine
and so in that case it would be that
console client's job
to make calls to the application however
it was configured
maybe it's a slash health endpoint so we
would actually be making those those
calls
the application and then it would be
noticing that it's down and then that's
how console would know that the
application is uh
no longer healthy okay
the next question i need to ask you will
have to be on load balancing up
there was an interesting discussion in
episode 264
i just listened to it a few days back
and james said that if i think the
question
that the host asked was if load
balancing was a part of service
discovery
and he answered that if service
discovery was done right
you wouldn't need load balancing what
are your thoughts on that
it's interesting i think
i think maybe i i can get out what he
meant by that
which is that if i say i have two
instances of a database and one of
them's
under load that when something's asking
me hey
what are the ip addresses of the
database perhaps my service discovery
mechanism
wouldn't return the ip address of the
database that's overloaded
and instead it would only return one ip
address of the one that's fine
and so that kind of that health
information
in the load information is is built into
the service discovery mechanism
however i think it's hard in service
discovery
harder to do this kind of thing than in
service mesh
it's just kind of like like any other
field in
in our technology area here where
sometimes you need that extra layer of
programmability and
extra layer control when we end up
putting all this stuff
into the proxy and the proxy is the one
that decides
where to wrote these requests you now
have just
basically infinite control over where
these requests route and what kind of
load balancing you want to do
so for example you might want to do load
balancing based on
i already sent 100 requests over to this
database instance i'm going to start
sending these requests over here
so that would kind of be like this
proxy's keeping track of its own where
it's been sending requests
but you might also want to do some more
complex load balancing around i notice
that this instance of the database
responds
way faster than this instance so i'm
just going to send all my traffic to the
one that's responding really really
quickly
this kind of locality aware load
balancing that is very very hard to
build
into a service discovery mechanism
because
how would the service discovery system
know that that place was closer to
that call would be faster for this
specific instance right
so you can see how when you get into it
there's a lot of
complexity and extra kind of goodies you
can get out of a service mesh because
you're
you're at the proxy and you have full
control and you also have full
observability into what's happening with
my requests at this level
you talked about observability and i was
going to ask about that later but i
think maybe it makes sense to us
now i read about service level
observability in the literature what
does this mean
do you have a a dashboard where i can
see new services or
how the communication requests are
happening right
yeah there's a there's a lot of acronyms
around there service level observability
service level objectives
so when we talk about like observability
as service level
really what we mean is there's metrics
that tell us what's happening with this
service
they'll be like application specific
metrics so you might
want to have a counter around how many
times
a specific endpoint has been called like
sign up or something like that
or you might want to have metrics around
how long your your database calls are
taking
so something you might want to alert on
there right when we look at
kind of where does this tie into the
service mesh
before the service mesh exists and you
just had your application your web
application calling your database
you could already instrument that so in
your code you could
put a start timer then you can make a
call out to the database
and then when the response comes back
you look at the time and you do
whatever how long did that take and then
you you call your metrics library and
you emit some sort of metric so maybe
that might fire off
over to like statsd or graphite or
something so we already had
this ability to instrument our
applications but
what we found was a you i now have to
write this code
which is kind of annoying because i want
to just focus on my business logic
and also i forgot to write this code
my name for this this time to talk to
the database was
request underscore time but the other
services
they called it request dash time and so
now when you're you know you're an
operator and you want to like kind of
look it i wonder how long calls to the
database you're taking
you now have you know 100 different
metrics names and
they're all using different technologies
to to emit these metrics right
or they haven't even instrumented it
where the service mesh helps with this
is again because everything's going
through this proxy now
we can emit the same name for that
metric
across all our different proxies we can
program the proxies to emit the
information
in prometheus data or graphite data so
we have uh kind of this full control now
where we can emit the same metrics if
the team hadn't
actually accidentally they hadn't
actually instrumented their calls to the
database it's not a problem because
all their calls go through our proxy so
we're definitely going to emit those
metrics
so that's where we see the service mesh
really really helping
with with this where you can kind of
have a metric observability into your
service
across all the different services across
your app across your infrastructure
we can talk about this later but again
not only can you now get this
information
but you can actually do something about
it right if you notice the calls to your
database are slow
you can maybe make a call okay well
we're going to spin up a second instance
of it
and we're going to start like routing 30
of the traffic to it or something like
that and you could control all this from
like the operation center basically
nice very cool maybe i can switch gears
a little bit into
what kind of support for infrastructure
you provide
i'm thinking in terms of how do you
integrate
networking with ci cd could you talk us
through that and maybe
as a uh what do you say uh the
maintainer of atlantis
we use that a lot as well yeah they're
connected in some ways and
disconnected in in other ways so when
we're talking about
deploying the service mesh itself
that is more kind of of a static thing
that you'll deploy a specific version of
console
and that will run for for a decent
amount of time infrastructure maybe
you'll update a release every couple
months to get the latest bug fixes or
whatever
you could kind of pick your your ci cd
pipeline of choice for for that
deployment probably it would be
whatever you use for your other services
and
console can run in kubernetes it can
also run on on virtual machines
so that's kind of how you would you
would do that and then
when we look at ci cd for our like
applications themselves
obviously you can just deploy those as
you would before and kind of the one
difference with the service mesh
is if you're running for example in
kubernetes
what we can do is we can intercept that
that request to hey deploy my web
service
and we can automatically add in this
proxy
to that and so when that web service
comes up it's now got that proxy already
running
and that proxy is already connected to
the console control plane
and boom now that that web services is
in the service mesh and we can
we can start to program its traffic and
do certain things with this traffic
but it can also come into play too where
when we are deploying a new version
of an application through through our
cicd pipeline maybe what we want to do
is we want to you know say we have 100
instances of it we want to deploy 10
using the new version
and do what's called a canary deployment
where we
route like a very small amount of our
traffic to those 10 new instances and
closely monitor the metrics this is
where
we can see that the power of being able
to program your network and do whatever
you want with the routing
it's going to be really easy to route
only 10 of our or only a small amount of
traffic to those 10 instances
when we have a service mesh and all of
our calls
are leaving proxies across our
infrastructure so we can just program
those proxies saying hey
if you're talking to the web service i
want you to send i want to send one
percent of your requests over to these
canary deployments
so when you talk about programming your
network what's the support so you you're
saying that you can define a new
configuration i guess
declaratively right right how do you do
that i guess
i'll let you answer that maybe right
yeah what we do is
is we have this basically configuration
and kubernetes is yaml
of course and basically we have lots of
different service meshes
have kind of their different their
different ways to configure this
in console we have a couple different
like types of configuration that let you
for instance we have this one called a
service splitter
where you can say identify for example
that canary deployment and you can say
hey i want to send 10 of my traffic
there
so what you would do is you would use a
custom resource
in kubernetes basically that has that
information that says hey
requests going to the web service i want
you to write 10 of them
over to the v2 of it when we look at
kind of if you're running on on vms
it's the same kind of thing but instead
of having a kubernetes ammo
we can do it via like an api call to
console with like
either json or hcl but it's basically
the same the same schema
and so yeah it's all controlled via a
kind of api
or in kubernetes it would be like a
yammer resource
okay perfect i was going to ask you
about a b testing support i think you've
kind of alluded to it now so this is the
service splitter right
right which you just talked about can
you explain that a little bit is that
like uh something on the configuration
that you set up
on your yaml file yeah for sure
so yeah it's exactly that it a b testing
would be
it's an interesting concept with in
terms of service mesh because
typically when i think when i at least
think of a b testing i think of a
consumer like a user
using my website and for instance i
serve the button in one case is blue and
the button in one case is red
and then i i have metrics around which
one
gets clicked more often kind of thing
right within like the web service
calling the database service
there's probably less use of the concept
of an a b test
but you definitely have this concept of
of needing to split traffic maybe a blue
green deployment or canary deployment
so yeah what we would do is you have
this this config
configuration entry where it would
identify
that i want to send a certain amount of
traffic to this service 50
for example and then i think what you
could probably do too is
is you could identify like separate
metrics for that for that request that
went over there
and you could kind of like see that on
your on your graphs that the traffic
that went to the blue button
you know there was more requests over
there or something like that so you
could kind of configure the the metrics
that got outputted there
okay perfect sounds good i got
my answers so that was great i would
like to now
switch gears so we talked about service
discovery we've done a little bit about
health monitoring
infrastructure support and my personal
favorite
security so you talked a little bit
about it
in the beginning but can you explain how
you handle security in terms of
authentication
and authorization for sure yeah and i'll
kind of
preface this discussion with what we've
seen and i'm sure if anyone's been a
security engineer at a company where
they move to a platform like kubernetes
for example
what we've typically seen for security
which is basically you have a firewall
you have security groups between your
apps and you have kind of this control
of like okay this
ip address 10.10.10 can talk to you know
ip address 10.10.05 or whatever
and i have this rule and it's listed
down and if i ever want to change it i
put a ticket into operations i change it
right very very static based security
we're we're moving into it we're already
there really into this new world where
it's too dynamic for that to happen in a
scheduler
you're going to have these pods with ip
addresses the change all the time they
come up and down
you can't have the these static ip
address lists right what we need to do
is focus on the
on the idea of like service identity so
it's not about this ip address port pair
that identifies a service
but instead that service needs to have
some other sort of identity that we can
use to
to authenticate it so when the web
service calls the database service how
do we know that it's the web service
we can't look at the source ip anymore
because that's changing so freak
so fast so and in addition in places
like kubernetes
by default unless you're running with
like network policy or whatever that the
network's totally flat so there is no
firewall rules
between what can talk to what by default
it's completely open anything can talk
to anything else
which developers love and and uh
security folks are probably probably
pretty scared about
so what we talk about in that case is
this idea of
a zero trust network where you can't
base your trust on who can talk to who
based on ip addresses
so so what do we use most service meshes
what they will do
is they'll actually use mtls mutual
tls and what that is is when the web
service talks the database service
it speaks over ssl so https not only
when i talk to so for instance when i
talk to google.com my browser will make
sure that the certificate served by that
is actually served and owned by
google.com so i can't get what's called
man in the middle
what mutual tls is is not only do i
verify that google.com is google.com
but google will verify that that this is
luke that's making this call to me
so when we go to our web and database
example
the web service gets a certificate that
actually identifies it as web
it's cryptographically verifiable it's
been signed by a trusted authority
that says yeah this is the web service
and so when that request goes over to
the database service
not only can the web service verify okay
i am talking to the database
i'm not sending my database password
somewhere incorrectly
but the database service can look at the
client certificate
which is coming from from the web
because that's a client it can
see that it's been cryptographically or
it's been signed by the trusted
authority
and that it actually is the web service
so that's kind of the first kind of the
first layer there is this idea of mutual
tls
so we both know who each other is and we
both are trusting that
each other is who we say we are and then
you have kind of
in console we call this intentions i'm
sure there's there's many different
names of it for the
different service meshes but it's
basically just an access control list
which says okay i know this is the web
service talking to me
are they allowed to talk to me and so we
look up our in our list and it says okay
yes web is allowed to talk to me
we have kind of you can go even deeper
with console we have this concept of
layer seven which is basically like you
could look at the http path that it's
using
so okay the web service is allowed to
call the payment service at
slash billing with like a get request
but it can't do like a post request to
like slash admin or something like that
so you could kind of get even deeper
into these these authorization and the
security layers
but the the overarching concepts are
this idea of mtls where
all communication is encrypted and over
ssl and then
each side of the party who's in part
into this communication
can verify that they're talking who do
they expect to be talking to
okay actually i was going to ask you
about zero trust because we did an
episode
385 on zero trust and you know one line
i just
i think you've explained it beautifully
but one line that really struck with me
uh during that episode
the host was actually quoting a google
engineer who said
do not trust your network it is probably
already owned
oh wow which is deep but you know
that kind of perfectly i think you've
answered it because if i were to
summarize what you said you really don't
trust any of the
new nodes that are coming up unless you
i mean you basically don't trust anyone
and then
it it all depends on your certificates
and this
mtls that you talked about and also you
said you have
further granularity right yeah i think
zero trust networking it sounds kind of
a bit
confusing maybe and and really what we
just mean is
you can't use uh firewall rules anymore
based on ip address
that's really what it is it's like it's
like you're running your all your
networks on like the public network
on ec2 public or whatever it used to be
called anybody can talk to you
and you can't just set up firewall rules
obviously you should have defense in
depth and you should actually have
firewall rules but
that's generally the concept there right
i guess you're uh
you can't just really trust that a
perimeter defense is
good and right it's longer safe exactly
yeah
also get back into what you talked about
you know this multi-platform
service mesh so i could have uh
like for example in my company we will
probably have a kubernetes cluster
running on azure and we do have
you know some legacy vm running some
important
jobs right there could be i mean there
are some vms in on our you know
our data center but we also have some
vms on another cloud provider like say
google
so how does console handle the situation
oops yeah this is something that is
extremely common
it's very very difficult to handle at
least in
in the world before service mesh we try
to make it a little bit easier
with the service mesh so what we have
the concept of
with console is this idea of a different
data centers however you can also think
of it as
different clusters they're really kind
of interchangeable there when you
have your your azure kubernetes cluster
running
and you have your your virtual machines
ideally what you want is
first of all you want that zero trust
networking
so you want when the legacy say the web
service that's running over
in in your azure cluster your aks
cluster wants to talk to the database
that's running on-prem
so that's maybe what you call it legacy
you want that request to be
encrypted obviously as it goes over
there so that's the first thing
and the second thing you want is you
actually want
it's actually not that easy probably to
route over
between the two of them because often
when we're talking about multiple
different data centers
clusters the networking spaces aren't
overlapping
and so you can't just take the pod ip
and talk to it from
your your on-prem data center that pod
ip
doesn't exist it doesn't know where to
wrote that right when we're talking
about
multiple clusters we need to add in this
concept of gateways
so gateways are kind of sitting on the
edge
and they have an ip address that is
routable
from either cluster so maybe it's a
public ip
or maybe it's still private but it's not
a pod ip
you know it's something that actually
exists that you can resolve so that's
kind of
the first key piece there is you need
this this thing that sits on the edge
that is rotable obviously you need to
get somewhere it needs to be vertical
we also have the concept of vpns where
everything's within the vpn so
everything is readable so in this case
you probably wouldn't eat this
gateway but then when you're talking
about a vpn we're kind of going back to
what we're talking about with this
perimeter security right
so we can't just like blindly trust our
vpn so that's the first thing we need
when we're talking about multi-data
center
the second thing we need to do is we
need to be able to communicate
what's running where and whether it's
healthy or not
right that seems pretty easy on the face
of it just make an api call and find out
but maybe one of the reasons we're
running multiple data centers is for
failover
and for reliability so what happens when
this data center goes down
this mechanism of understanding what's
running in each data center needs to be
really resilient to failure those are
kind of the main concepts at play here
or is like the routability
usually through gateways there's the
security aspect of it so
you say that you're the database how can
i trust that you actually are the
database
and then there's kind of the reliability
and
failover aspects of it so concretely
what that means in console is
we would have you set up a data center
console data center which is basically
just a set of console like processes
running in in your aks application
install it through the helm chart and
then you'd also set up a set of console
servers
in your your on-prem cluster there your
legacy cluster
and those would be connected and they
would trust each other through
a set of shared certificates and then
depending on how your
how your networking is set up we would
have some gateways on the edge
so that we could actually like call
between the two data centers
and then when the the web server is
running in in azure wants to talk to the
database
it just talks to its local proxy and
that proxy
handles it from there under the hood
what it's doing is it's going to be
it's going to be using a certificate
it's going to be recognizing that the
database isn't
in in azure it's actually over in this
other cluster this legacy cluster
it's going to be sending it over to the
the gateway
for that legacy cluster the gateway is
then going to be
looking at the request it's going to see
that it's signed by a trusted
certificate
it's going to let that request through
and then it's going to be routed
directly to
the databases proxy and then it would
the proxy is going to look at that
request it's going to look at the
certificate it's going to say okay it's
from the web service and web is allowed
to talk to me
and it's going to route over to the
database so under the hood it's actually
quite complicated but
from the perspective of each cluster
it's kind of easy you just talk to your
proxy and everything gets handled from
there
okay sounds probably easier also because
you're directly just talking to your
local proxy so
yeah definitely each application doesn't
really need to know
where other applications are so say you
were to migrate that database
later somewhere else you could just do
that and make sure you don't have to
really make any changes to the web
service you want to redeploy or anything
okay i wanted to also like
find out from you if you could again
elaborate a little bit about this
failure and retries because i think uh
all this distributed
communication needs this infrastructure
support for this scenario right
can you just like go over that again
yeah for sure so as we saw
the move from monolith to microservices
what you used to have was your
function call now was actually a network
call and occasionally that would fail
so we started at least what i did what
we used to use to do was we would
build some like some for loops into our
code
where if it fails just retry it again
basically you end up writing a bunch of
logic in your application that handles
kind of these failures
and then you know some somebody would
get fancy and they'd implement like
exponential back off or something like
that right
but each application developer needed to
do this uh themselves
in every single application for every
single network call at least what
what we found was someone would have
something right
where they're like well we really need
this call to succeed so we're going to
retry 20 times
what would happen is that that service
they're calling maybe it gets a bit slow
and so maybe that first call doesn't
succeed and suddenly
it's getting hammered with 20 times of
traffic
because this application in it in its
wisdom is just retrying the call
a ton of times and now the application
is actually hard down because it's
getting 20 times as much traffic as it
used to
so that's kind of setting the stage for
for where we
where we started to go as an industry
and there were libraries out there that
would kind of be smarter and
but you know that was kind of the
problems we had to solve and so
what we get with the service mesh now is
don't write a for loop in your
application that tries this network call
20 times instead try it once
send it out to the proxy and now inside
the proxy we can
control that 20 loop maybe we do want it
to loop
20 times but maybe the service is down
and we actually only want it to
to loop once or to wait five seconds
before
it tries again now all this logic kind
of gets put into the proxy
and then we can configure it similar to
what we were talking about before with
the service split we would have a
configuration file or a yaml file
which basically configures the behavior
for failover
and i can go quickly over kind of the
different things you could do
so one thing you could do is you could
retry you could retry with an
exponential back off
you could do a circuit breaker pattern
where you recognize that that service is
hard down
and so instead of making the application
who's making that call wait for like uh
one second until the call times out
you just fail it right away so
immediately that call fails
the application still needs to deal with
the fact that call failed but it doesn't
have to wait one second
which might mean like you get an error
page really quickly from a user
instead of you know having to wait for
the for your call to timeout
and another thing we can do when we did
just talk about multi-cluster but we
could maybe look at
failing that request over to one of this
other clusters that
we think is is still up and running so
ideally
we only talk to our local cluster
because it's faster but in in times of
trouble we might fail over to this other
cluster over here
that the call takes a bit longer but at
least it succeeds that's kind of what we
look at when we look at how do we how do
we handle failure
and the only other thing i'll add is
that when we go back to observability
we now have a common set of metrics with
which to diagnose that this is failing
so these very complicated architectures
will have
every single proxies emitting a metric
that's saying the database is down
that's pretty darn good information the
database is down
that's just got me thinking a lot of
stuff
yeah exactly yeah but coming back to the
episode
yeah so this is great i mean if if i
were to just recap what we've just
spoken about we've
you know you led us through service
discovery um
health monitoring and right now we spoke
about this
multi-cloud support and also this
failure
and retry scenarios can we step back and
also talk a little bit uh which i should
have asked you in the beginning but i
got so into this uh
but uh could you tell us about how this
control plane and the data plane work
you know with console and envoy for sure
yeah
so at a high level when we think about
data plane what we mean is
each application calling the other
applications through the proxies
so this is the the data so if you try to
it's kind of hard on a podcast but
visualizing your head you have like
on the bottom of the diagram we have
like application web talking application
database
and they're both talking through a proxy
that's the data plane
and then above all that sits the control
plane
so this is a console or a sdo and this
is
talking to the proxies so it doesn't
talk to the application
it configures the proxies now obviously
there's a lot less
communication going on here but you know
the control plane needs to tell the
proxy hey
split half of your traffic over here or
hey
i want you to retry every one second or
something for this
so that's what we call the control plane
so the data plane is
the application is talking to each other
through the proxies and the control
plane
is what's controlling all the proxies
perfect
the next logical thing which i've not
covered right now is
also about performance and how does that
work
with having this extra layer with
console like do you do something similar
like you do something of a clients who
demand that you do something special for
performance critical applications yeah
that's a that's a great question
and i think that is something that's
often missed when we talk about kind of
the wonders of service meshes
there is or there can be a performance
implications
because you're taking this request that
used to leave your application
and go over to this other one and now
that's hitting some other process
which now has its own memory and it
needs to process these and see these cpu
cycles to process it
and maybe it's doing some complicated
things maybe it's doing ssl like
right so it's not it's definitely not a
free lunch
if you're talking about extremely
low latency applications where
microseconds matter
then adding a proxy in front of
everything is definitely going to
make an impact to your application
and if there's there's other
developments around like ebpf
this idea where why don't we do a
service mesh but we do it inside
the linux kernel itself so it's a lot
faster so we don't have to go kind of
swap back into user space so there are
there are developments with these kind
of extremely low latency
requirements but i think what's worth
mentioning is that
most applications don't notice
microseconds
they're going to notice a couple of
milliseconds but a couple microseconds
are not going to make a big difference
instead what makes a big difference is
being able to
build applications faster deploy them
migrate them
control them and handle failure faster
so for many of kind of the microservices
use cases
the extra performance hit you get from a
service mesh is
well worth all the control you're
getting
and in some cases it's actually faster
because in the case of load balancing
where we're able to intelligently route
to the
applications that's closest to us
whereas before we were kind of just
blindly firing off to
all the different instances available
you could actually see your requests
actually complete faster
because you're talking to the one that's
closest to you there is a performance
hit and
it's not negligible but in general what
we find
is that it's it doesn't make a huge
difference to these applications we're
talking about maybe an extra
couple milliseconds the control it gives
you is well worth it
now that we've sort of covered a range
of things that the console does
how would you differentiate it against
the other service meshes out there like
sdo or linkedin console what we're very
focused on
is this idea of multiple platforms so
consoles started out of out of virtual
machines
a lot of the service meshes kind of were
kubernetes first
and kubernetes only some of them still
are so
that's a big thing for us is this idea
of
how can we make a kind of a the ux the
the user experience of the service mesh
and how to deploy it the same across
multiple platforms be it kubernetes or
ecs or vms so i'd say that's kind of
what
what we focus on as our differentiator
and then also
we i'll do focus two on like tie-ins to
other hashicorp products so for instance
like
if you're using fault then you can use
like vault to control some of the
security of the console service mesh
so that's kind of what what we what we
think of as kind of our special sauce
there is is multi-platform
and then we also have a program called
the hashicorp cloud platform
where you can actually get a hosted
version of console so you don't have to
manage kind of all the operational
complexities of running your own service
mesh
so that's another really really big
initiative for us where we have our own
team of sres that kind of
manage this for you and again because
we're
we're not owned by a specific cloud
provider we can provide this across
different clouds and we can provide
multi-cloud support
um so that's another another thing that
i think is worth calling out is kind of
like we
we're always about multi-cloud
multi-platform and we don't really have
like specific tie into a specific cloud
so i think that's kind of like the the
differentiators for us there
but they're all great i think all the
services are good and
depending on your use case and and and
what you're doing i think all the folks
working
in the service mesh industry are doing
really really cool stuff
okay okay so can you you know suggest
some good resources for our listeners to
you know look up on console
absolutely this podcast would be great
but you're already listening
[Laughter]
i like that we have uh i think the best
place for for folks to start is
we have a really great website called
learn.hashicorp.com
and it's all about kind of these
hands-on tutorials for kind of just
getting jumping into the tool and at
least personally that's how i like to
learn
of course you can you can read all the
documentation too but i like to just
play around with things so
i think that's a probably where i would
tell folks to start is go to
learn.hashgroup.com
look at the console different tutorials
we have there and just start
start walking through it get get console
installed and start messing around with
it
and i think that's a really great place
to start okay i'll make sure that
i put that in our show notes okay where
can people reach you
if they wanted to like touch base like
somewhere on twitter
yeah the best place to reach me is on
twitter my username is
l k y s o w
el kaiso so yeah hit me up on twitter
and my dms are open and i'm happy to to
discuss
anything thank you so much for this uh
interesting conversation i feel very
enlightened like buddha
so thank you so much for having me
good luck on on your your database woes
at work
thank you this is priyanka raghwan for
software engineering
radio and i hope you like the show
thanks for listening to sc
radio an educational program brought to
you by ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening